In one of your lectures, you mentioned
that P equals NP is philosophically
about the fundamental limits of human
knowledge. What is P equals NP, and how
does it relate to human knowledge?
>> Right in the
simplest way, and I will talk at a high
level.
Uh, we are interested in
various problems in life, and all sorts
of problems, mathematical problems,
scientific problems, medical problems,
personal problems, intellectual
problems. We are in the business in
computer science of solving problems by
computers.
Now,
uh,
we would like to somehow classify uh,
those problems that we can solve.
Right? To know what we can know. What
the problems we can solve are the things
we will know, we will understand. So,
there are all those problems that we
want to understand. There are many of
them.
Uh, and there are the problems that we
can understand, can solve.
Okay?
In a very basic way, the first class is
NP. All the problems we want to solve
are really NP problems.
So, it's a class of problems.
Uh, a subset of which is the problems we
can solve. They are the problems we can
currently solve, but we are interested
in all the problems we can solve
in principle, we can ever, you know,
really solve. So, the question of P
versus NP is whether we can solve all
the problems we want to solve, whether
we can know everything we want to know.
This is basically about the limits of
our knowledge.
Of course, I have to justify why, you
know, these classes, which are
mathematically defined, actually are
captured by these intuitive um,
intuitive meanings I'm giving them. P is
very easy to justify. What we can solve
is what we can
uh, you know, solve in our lifetime
using whatever we have, let's say all
computers that we uh,
have using efficient algorithms. So,
problems we can solve are problems you
see in our apps in our phones, like
if there's a navigation app, it means
somebody invented an algorithm that's
efficient enough to solve any you know,
shortest path problem between any and
any two places in any kind of map.
Okay.
Uh, why are all the problems we want to
solve are NP problems?
What is NP? NP is a class of problems, a
mathematical definition, uh,
problems so that, you know, whether
they're easy or hard to solve, we don't
know, but if somebody hands us a
solution,
then we can easily check that indeed it
is a good solution.
Now, why
are all problems we humanity is
interested in of this nature? You can
think there's no limit to what we may
want to know.
But I claim that essentially in any
human endeavor, the
if you're embarking on any problem, if
you really seriously want to solve a
problem, the least you want to know
is that when you hit upon a solution,
you'll recognize it as a solution.
I mean, why would you ever start on
looking for something if you would never
recognize it as
what you looked for?
So, you think mathematicians are
looking, uh, for proofs of theorems?
Certainly, if somebody gives a proof,
you know, wrote the paper about it, we
can verify.
If a scientist wants to explain data,
uh, you know, about the planets or
about, I don't know,
the, you know, bacteria or whatever,
uh,
you know, we want to develop a theory,
so that's what you're searching for in
this case.
And yeah, we again, scientists write
papers about their theories, they have
to be consistent with the data. We have
a way of recognizing that this is a good
solution.
Engineers
uh you know, are usually tasked with
creating something, bridge or phone or
you know,
something
uh under some constraints. It can be
monetary constraints, physical
constraints, all sorts of you can use
this but not this and so on. But anyway,
if an engineer designs something,
whoever gave them their task can look at
it and say, "Well, you you
violated some constraints." Or no, it's
good. You you you really delivered what
we were looking for. So, I'm giving you
examples. I mean, I can give many more.
Detectives are supposed to solve crimes
and you know, we know from detective
books, you know, they eventually
provide. So,
these are examples of very fundamental
human endeavors that are, you know,
encompass almost everything I can think
of. In all of them, what people are
searching for have the property that
when a solution is found,
it is easily recognized.
So,
uh repeating the beginning, NP are all
problems that we can honestly say we
really want to solve. And P are those
that we can solve. Whether they are
equal, you know, if they are equal, then
everything we would want to know, cure
for cancer, uh you
anything you imagine,
uh can be, uh you know, just the very
fact that
a solution can be easily recognized
would imply that it can be efficiently
found.
That means that we can know everything
we ever want to know. It's a fundamental
question about human knowledge.